<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse to the lords of the Parliament As touching the murther committed vppon the person of Henrie the Great, King of Fraunce. Manifestlie prooving the Iesuites to be the plotters and principall deuisers of that horrible act. Translated out of French, and published by authority.</title>
            <title>Remonstrance à messieurs de la Cour de Parlement sur le parricide commis en la personne du roy Henry le Grand. English</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103959</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839701</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839701</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02994)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 727:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse to the lords of the Parliament As touching the murther committed vppon the person of Henrie the Great, King of Fraunce. Manifestlie prooving the Iesuites to be the plotters and principall deuisers of that horrible act. Translated out of French, and published by authority.</title>
                  <title>Remonstrance à messieurs de la Cour de Parlement sur le parricide commis en la personne du roy Henry le Grand. English</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>Crashaw, William, 1572-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas]: P[urfoot]: for Na: Butter, and are to be sold at his shop at S. Augustines Gate, in Paules Church yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: William Crashavve.</note>
                  <note>A translation of "Remonstrance à messieurs de la Cour de Parlement sur le parricide commis en la personne du roy Henry le Grand", attributed to Philippe de Mornay.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A relation to the lords of the Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Assassination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  France --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE TO THE LORDS OF the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AS TO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CHING THE</hi> Murther committed vppon <hi>the perſon of</hi> HENRIE the Great, King of Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MANIFESTLIE PROOVING <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and principall</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>TRANSLATED O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T OF <hi>French, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed by</hi> T. P. <hi>for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and are to be ſold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> RICHARD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet; <hi>and his Noble &amp; vertuous Lady the Lady</hi> ANNE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Honour and all happineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Christ.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F <hi>Origen,</hi> it was vſually ſayd amongſt the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets: <hi>where he did wel none did better; where ill, none worſe</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Vbi bene, nemo meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: vbi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, nemo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius.</note>: And of thoſe good Bookes he wrote, (which were very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) learned <hi>Hierom</hi> ſayth, that as in thoſe Bookes he excelled all others: ſo <note n="b" place="margin">Hieron. in praefat in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. Homel. in Caut: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oper H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron. in Tom. 3.</note> in his Homilies on the Cantickles, hee ſurpaſt himſelfe. Accordingly (but in the euill ſence which beſt be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts them) may it bee ſayd of the <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> that as in their trickes they haue played, and garboiles they haue
<pb facs="tcp:4147:3"/> raiſde, and villanies they haue commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe laſt fifty years, they haue gone beyond all men: ſo in their twoo laſt exploytes, namely the powder plotte of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Kings murther, they haue excelled themſeluees the truth whereof is moſt apparant, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee reſpect their <hi>Subtilty</hi> in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and <hi>Malice</hi> in performing; or their <hi>Craft</hi> in concealing, and <hi>Impudencie</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying both theſe actions. For, as to the two firſt, what Nation euer receaued ſuch a blowe, and was ſtrucken into ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement; as <hi>France</hi> in the death of their great <hi>Henrie?</hi> And what firme and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſtate in the world, was euer vpon a ſodain, covered with ſuch a deſolation, as <hi>England</hi> had, if bleſſed <hi>Ieſus</hi> had not confounded the curſed <hi>Ieſuites</hi> plot?</p>
            <p>And for the two latter, who knoweth not that though all Records haue regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred them, and moſt nations of the world proclaimed them the founders and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the pouder Treaſon; yet had they not onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contriued to haue caſt it vpon
<pb facs="tcp:4147:3"/> others, if it had taken effect: but ſince it miſcarryed, haue not bluſhed to publiſhe in print <note n="c" place="margin">Iac. Gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerus in ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico pa. 41 4 &amp;c.</note>: that the Ieſuites were no way guilty of it, that <hi>Garnet</hi> was executed not for it, but onely for being a Prieſt: That he was rackt almoſt to death to make him confeſſe himſelfe guilty, but neuer did: and that <hi>Oven</hi> his man was plucked in pieces on the racke, becauſe he would not accuſe his Maſter: whereas the world knowes, Records teſtifie, and thouſands liue, whoſe eares and eyes can witneſſe, all theſe particulars that enſue:</p>
            <p n="1">1 That <hi>Garnet</hi> the Provinciall (with his ſix names) &amp; other Ieſuits were found guilty of the powder Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That <hi>Garnet</hi> was arraigned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed onely for that.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That he freely and openly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed both at his tryall and his death, he had neuer been on the racke in his life.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That he confeſſed (without torture) he knew of the powder-plot in confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That he firſt denyed and forſwore this and diuerſe other matters which hee
<pb facs="tcp:4147:4"/> afterwards confeſſed, and defended the ſame by aequiuocation.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That <hi>Oven</hi> confeſt he kild himſelfe with his owne knife, to avoide the racke, leaſt it ſhould make him confeſſe ſuch things as he had rather dye than diſcover.</p>
            <p>All theſe thinges are as cleere as the Noone day, and yet (forſooth) the good ſeely innocent <hi>Ieſuites</hi> muſt not bee held guilty of the powder treaſon: but what ſhall we ſay to this impudency; if it do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that not onely <hi>Garnet</hi> and his Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh brethren, but all the great <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in the world, were priuie to that plot? what ſhall we thinke, if the very caſe <hi>in terminis,</hi> (the powder treaſon in the particular cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances) were propounded, debated, and reſolued amongſt the Ieſuits before it came to paſſe? what if <hi>Garnet</hi> was reſolued from the principall Father of the ſociety, that though hee knewe the particulars of ſuch a plotte, yet hee ought not by any meanes to reveale it? I for my part will be but the reporter, let the wiſe reader iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delrio</hi> a great and famous Ieſuite, puts <note place="margin">d Mart. Delrio: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ. magic: Tom. 3. lib. 6. ca. 1. ſect. 2: &amp;c.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4147:4"/> this caſe not long before the pouder trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: A Prieſt is made priuie in confeſſion, that in ſuch a vault or vnder ſuch a houſe ſuch a quantity of gunpouder is purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly layd, as if it be not remooued there is evident danger, that not only much peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but euen the Prince himſelfe are ſure to bee murthered. The <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> mooues what the confeſſor is to do in this caſe: &amp; for anſwere hee cannot but confeſſe, that moſt Doctors hold, hee ought with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and warineſſe to diſcouer it: but for concluſion he reſolues, that the ſafer and better opinion is, he ought to conceale it: Wherby (Right Ho:) your Lordſhip and all the world may ſee, that if <hi>Garnet</hi> did conceale the powder treaſon, hee did no more then he had the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> reſolution aforehand for his warrant in that caſe. If then, <hi>Garnet</hi> were arraigned and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely for being priuie to the plot: If it be knowen to all, that he was privie to it by confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to ſome that he knew of it otherwiſe alſo then by confeſſion: If he was neuer on the racke, and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:4147:5"/> never put to confeſſe all he know: If <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> his man choſe rather to kill himſelfe, then confeſſe all he knew of the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in that matter: If the very caſe of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der treaſon <hi>(in terminis terminantibus</hi> as the Lawyers ſay) was debated and reſolved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> If theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars I ſay, be true, may any reaſonable man make queſtion any longer, whether the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> be guilty of that plot?</p>
            <p>And nomore queſtion is there (if all were knowne) that they were the forgers, the Authors, and Abbetors of this late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous and fearefull french murder: and let them not doubt; but the Author of truth and reuenger of all bloud (but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of his anointed) will vnmaske them and diſcouer it to the full: they plot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d it in helliſh darkeneſſe, but God will reveals it, and their ſhame by it, in the ſight of the ſonne and face of all the world.</p>
            <p>This little Booke (amongſt others, which lately <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath ſent vs) hath begunne this diſcovery, and Truth will not reſt crying to God, till it be ſo perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:4147:5"/> that all the world may ſee it: And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Authority iudged it fit and woorthy to paſſe in <hi>Engliſh</hi> to publique viewe, it was held not vnfitting in fewe woords to let the world know, that this Author (tho a ſtraunger) hath ſpoken (touching the great Engliſh Treaſon) no more then knowen truth: and which, if they dare deny it, or any part of it, ſhal be more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly deciphered and averred to their faces, by evidences vndeniable, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all exception: Let them accept the condition when they pleaſe, it will be performed on our parts.</p>
            <p>In the meane time (Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) accept this, and giue it reading, as a Teſtimonie of the love and ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect my heart doth owe you: who as I will ever pray, that you may ſtill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour GOD and your ſelues, by zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Poperye, and conſtancye in the Truth: So ſhall I reioyce by anye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I can perfourme, to bee an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:4147:6"/> of your Confirmation in the ſame. Till when, giue mee leaue to bee one of thoſe, who will euer honour your Noble and Religious vertues, and who in all Chriſtian and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affection, doth vowe to remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours ſervant in Christ, WILLIAM CRASHAVV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:6"/>
            <head>A RELATION TO <hi>the Lordes of the Parliament,</hi> concerning the death of their <hi>KING.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hall wee then looſe our King? the moſt mightie and puiſſant King that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>France</hi> foſtered, that ever <hi>Europe</hi> contayned, for the ſpace of 500. yeares. The heart that gaue life to the bodie of this State, even vnto the leaſt Arterie: The naturall heat, the force &amp; vigour of ſo many ſoules, is pierced, is ſlaine with the accurſed knife of a damned Caytife: &amp; ſhall he for ſo ſtrange and inhumane a fact, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no greater torture or torment, than this baſe and ordinary puniſhment? Shall this bee iudged a ſacrifice ſufficient for ſo hainous a treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe? Shall this be delivered vnto poſterity for our ſhame, and ſuffered of vs in theſe our dayes
<pb facs="tcp:4147:7"/> to our vtter ruine and confuſion? And you my Lordes of this Parliament, that owe to him Iuſtice, and ought to doe your ſelues right, are you at a ſtand? reſt you now amazed? you that through the height of your wiſedomes, are able to vnfolde the moſt difficult pointes of dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt cauſes, are you now at a ſtand, and beſides your ſelues in a matter ſo cleare and evident? You buſily enquire after the Authors of this prodigious bloody blow; and yet you perfectly vnderſtand, that the knife was but the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Ravailac,</hi> of <hi>Ravailac;</hi> ſet on, induced, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by other: It was others that put the knife into his hand, and planted the murther in his heart.</p>
            <p>And is it then ſuch a matter for you that are men of ſuch wiſedome, gravity, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to devine, coniecture, nay abſolutely to convince who thoſe Abettors are?</p>
            <p>Seeing that all Chriſtendome by general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent concluded, that ſince the creation of the world, there hath not any ſect or ſocietie beene found more capable or more culpable in ſuch villanies, than the Ieſuits and their confederates, and doe you make a doubt thereof?</p>
            <p>Haue not Murtherers riſen again in our dayes of Chriſtian kings, the remnants of Sarazin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie, and race of the Mores, who haue written books, erected ſchooles, wherin they teach the Methode
<pb facs="tcp:4147:7"/> ther and manner of murthering Kings? Haue they not reduced this monſtrous and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous practife into an Art, into a Caball? haue they not theſe many yeres framed and faſhioned mens minds by their miſteries and meditations, by their conſecrations and execrations, to this end purpoſe? are they honoured for any other exploytes, or magnified for any other miracles? Your owne lawes tell and teach vs; that hee that hath once beene conuinced of villanie, is euer after preſumed to bee a bird of the ſame feather.</p>
            <p>Sithence then their Emanuell in the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Confeſſors, decreeth, that it is lawfull to kill their King; that euery Clarke may without offence exempt himſelfe from the ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his naturall Prince; and further, aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and auoucheth, that hee cannot bee iuſtly termed a rebell, whatſoeuer he doth, or in what matter ſoeuer hee medleth, what ſhall wee thinke?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Mariana</hi> is yet more bolde and broad in <note place="margin">Iohn Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana de inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutione Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio. l. 1. c. 6. &amp; 7.</note> theſe buſineſſes, he is more particuler and more methodicall in theſe affaires; he ſtrideth a ſtep beyond all the reſt of his crewand company. He maintaineth flatly and plainly, that whoſoeuer hath a charge committed vnto him by the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Ieſuites, or from the hand of their Viſitor: or vnder the commaund of a fewe graue and learned perſons of that rancke; nay, without
<pb facs="tcp:4147:8"/> feare or daunger, attempt and aſſaile the perſon of his Prince or King, by pollicie, treaſon, or poyſon; nay he ſpareth not to repeate the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſorts and kinds of poyſon: as ſwift, or ſlow in working, giuen in drinke, or in meates, by touching of his ſacred and annoynted body, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a friendly prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of offring him ſome excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent preſent: or ſaith he, after the manner of the kings of the <hi>Moores;</hi> by rubbing his garments, his Chayre, his Linnen, his Armour, his Saddle, Stirrops, or Bootes.</p>
            <p>And further he warranteth, that whoſoeuer ſhall looſe his life in ſuch an attempt, ſhall doe a thing acceptable with God, and praiſe-worthy among men: hee ſhall bee (forſooth) a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice in the noſthrils of the Lord of hoaſtes.</p>
            <p>Theſe Bookes paſſed not their Authors with a ſtreight hand, nor were they compoſed or compiled by nouices: for the Emanuell (as he ſaith in his preface) was a worke of 40. yeares forging. The ordinarie Manuell of the Father Confeſſors. The Author therof, was among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man of ſuch fanctimony, as for his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Petrus Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badeneira</hi> in his Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. p. 14</note> holyneſſe, the Virgin Marie (ſay they) and their good Father <hi>Ignatius</hi> appeared vnto him at his death. That of <hi>Iohn Martana</hi> mencioned in the Catalogue of the bookes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> pa. 3. L. 141.</note> of their ſociety, publiſhed by Father <hi>Peter Ribadeneira,</hi> in the yeare 1608. with ſinguler
<pb facs="tcp:4147:8"/> commendation of the Author and his woorkes, as quallified with an excellent iudgement, with admirable learning, with profound Diuinity, that he taught in <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Sicile,</hi> and in <hi>Paris</hi> it ſelfe. Both of them imprinted with Anthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke priuiledges, approbations, and ſolemnities of their ſuperiors: the firſt at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> the other at <hi>Toledo</hi> and <hi>Maience;</hi> But the latter which ſhould ſtrike the greater ſtroake, was moſtcuriouſly and cunningly framed, to carry the greater authority, beſides it bore in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front greater recommendation; as the cenſure and approbation in <hi>Spaine</hi> by Frier <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Onna Prouinciall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſufferance to be imprinted giuen by <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Hoieda</hi> viſitor of the ſociety of <hi>Ieſus</hi> in the prouince of <hi>Toledo.</hi> And conſequently the full power and authority of pasſing current, was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and graunted to this Booke by the Father Generall of their ſociety, ſo highly commended by them, <hi>Claudius Aquauina:</hi> after approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, theſe are his wordes: By graue and learned perſonages of our order.</p>
            <p>Can you any longer doubt (my good Lords) when you ſo euidently ſee, out of what forge, &amp; of what temper this mettall is? Eſpecially when it is too well knowen to you all, what attempts within theſe 30. yeares, this ſect or ſociety haue made vpon the ſacred perſons and lyues of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kings &amp; Princes of Chriſtendome, &amp; pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:4147:9"/> ouer ſome. When that diuelliſh and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable gunpowder deuiſe of <hi>England</hi> reſteth ſo freſh in your memories, ſo bleeding new, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was purpoſed that the King, Queen, Prince, the whole Nobilitie of the Land, the whole Clergie, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and others, the chiefe and choice of the Commons, infinite numbers of all ſorts and qualities; in briefe, the beſt of the lands eſtate, without any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or acceptation of Religion or the Religious, albeit there were at that preſent aſſembled (as all the world knoweth) a number of both ſorts in that companie, ſhould equally without care had, or regard, or reſpect made, beene miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and monſtrouſly (by blowing vp the houſe wherein they were contained) muthered and maſſacred.</p>
            <p>Father <hi>Garnet</hi> by name their Prouinciall in <hi>England,</hi> with all his equiuocations, conuinced by his confederates, nay, by his own confeſsion, to be the Author, Director, and Executor of that thrice horrible actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if God of his ſingular grace and goodneſſe had not preuented the ſame: was yet by their ſect and ſort onely for attempting ſo diuelliſh and deteſtable an enterprize, as to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp and vtterly deuour ſo worthy an Eſtate: in ſtead of a thouſand tortures and torments due vnto his deſert, open declared and denounced holie, Canonized amongſt their Martires, imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſold, and in ſacred tearmes ſet out with this
<pb facs="tcp:4147:9"/> title: By him that is conſecrated to poſterity.</p>
            <p>And can any man yet doubt, that this murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Society vnder their hipocriticall maske, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yne, lodged this pouder, and were ready to put fire to their frame? who or what bee they that reward thus theſe fire-forgers? what are they that crowne thus theſe miſchiefe making Martyres? for ſo they ſay they are, and for ſuch they ſet them to ſale.</p>
            <p>Now, if theſe be their Martyres, what kind of ones (I pray you) are their Angells? But let vs wade yet a little deeper, what ſaye you to this, that Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the Champion and chiefetaine of that ſect, their generall Doctor, in an expreſſe Treatiſe written of purpoſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolleth and with great commendation exalteth, the murther that <hi>I ames Clement</hi> committed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the perſon of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third: which <hi>Mariana</hi> dareth auouch, did proceede from the ſtrong hand of the ſpirit of God, working in the weakneſſe of his bodie, who conſecrated (as he ſpeaketh) that knife to that intent and purpoſe, being rubbed ouer with venomous hearbs.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Rhibadenira, Bec anus, Vaſkes, Bonarſius,</hi> with many others after him, vnto the booke compoſed by the Ieſuites of <hi>Paris;</hi> Of the iuſt expulſion of <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, giue this Preface: That in a common cauſe one may lawfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, depoſe, yea, and ſlay if neede were <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:10"/>
            <p>Tell me I pray you, in the execution of this monſtrous controuerſie, what deuiſe, what ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageme, what practiſe was there among all the attempts made againſt the life of our King; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome Ieſuite or other had not a hand, or was not chiefe? yea, euen in that namely of <hi>Iohn Chaſtell,</hi> that ſtabde the king in the mouth where you (my Lordes) knewe, and euidently found, that he was inſtructed and induced by Ieſuites to ſtrike that ſtroke.</p>
            <p>As firſt, by the leſſons &amp; confeſsions of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holie Father <hi>Iohn Gueret;</hi> and next, by thoſe execrable poſitions of Father <hi>Iohn Guignard,</hi> both whome, you did condemne for the ſame their filthy fact, and with them the whole ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by a moſt ſolemne decree.</p>
            <p>And doe you yet ſtay for further proofe? Doe you doubt from the ſame iudgement ſeat, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer the ſame ſentence, and vſe the ſame execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon thoſe that be guilty of the ſame crime, of the ſame murder?</p>
            <p>Why, adde then this to thereſt, that the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites being not contented to haue razed your Pyramides ſet vp to leaue a memory to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of ſo inhumane and vnnaturall a fact, and therewithall defaced your decree fixed vppon the ſame; haue beſides within theſe few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths at <hi>Rome</hi> cenſured your decree againſt <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell,</hi> and conſequently ſought to diſcredite your Soueraigne authority; why then ſhould they
<pb facs="tcp:4147:10"/> not be held for fellow-offenders? that ought rather aboue others deteſt ſo bloodie a fact, and by deteſtation thereof, ſhew their inocencie? But they bolſter it vp, they alowe of it, they maintaine it; and all to weaken your iuſtice, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretended power of theirs, to haue ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie ouer all men.</p>
            <p>Now, after all this to make vp the meſſe of their miſchiefe, leaſt any thing ſhould bee wanting to the heape of their helliſhnes, they haue moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie painted forth a Kalender of their ſuppo, ſed Martirs made at <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſet to the ſhewe among vs, wherein they haue appointed ſeueral ſeates for thoſe faithleſſe Fathers <hi>Gueret,</hi> and <hi>Guignard,</hi> Maiſter, teachers, and confeſſors of <hi>Chaſtell,</hi> and condemned for the ſame crime.</p>
            <p>And why all theſe? but to confirme and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite the arme and blowe of the traiterous exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner, by exalting the praiſe and place, of <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, Gueret,</hi> &amp; <hi>Guignard?</hi> and ſo to confirme the minde of the murtherer with this imaginarie comfort, againſt the ſlanderous ignominie of the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And whereas three moneths after, our king de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded at <hi>Rome</hi> the reaſon of their ſo cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his decree, and reſtauration of the ſame: you ſee the blame was laid vppon our <hi>Fraunce;</hi> and whence (I pray you) ſhall it bee ſaid that this happeneth? forſooth by reaſon of that ſacred perſon, ſo often attempted and aſſailed with one
<pb facs="tcp:4147:11"/> and the ſame comſpiracie, with the ſelfe-ſame ſnares and engines, which hath been negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie looked vnto.</p>
            <p>But you ſeeke yet more plaine and expreſſe proofe. I would it were ſo, not ſo much for your conſciences, as our knowledge.</p>
            <p>Are you ignorant, or will you not know, that theſe peſtilent people doe traine vp for ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh practiſes, the moſt accurſed perſons that they can find, who after they haue confeſſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them their filthy and abhominable liues, as inceſts, the ſinne of <hi>Sodome,</hi> conuerſing with brute beaſts, and the like, (for other manner of men are not fit for their fingring): they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhew them hell, with their euerlaſting paines thereof, readie gapping to ſwallow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes they promiſe vnto them (but with promiſe, if they wil murther ſuch, or ſuch a one) to draw them from this deuouring gulfe, and plant them in Paradice, at the leaſt among the Angells; threatning them in the meane ſpace, that if they did not what was inioyned them, they ſhould haue hell with out all redemption or remiſsion for their inheritance, and double tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture if they diſcouered their confeſſors.</p>
            <p>By theſe ſuperſtitious impreſsions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching charmes, they are armed and embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt all torture or tormenr whatſoeuer, and are vtterlie left voide of any feeling of a good conſcience.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:11"/>
            <p>And did not that moſt monſtrous miſchiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worker himſelfe deliuer enough vnto you, how he was brought to ſermons, eſpeciallie thoſe of the laſt Aduent, and Lent, and whoſe ſermons were they? none but the Ieſuites, who filled all our mindes with ſedition, to incenſe all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Citie, who praiſed the tongues of our Curates, if they would haue giuen eare to their alluring words: for who ſaw not, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they ſpake there, were it of the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it tended to euill purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Did not the ſame Monſter, the ſame murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, (whome you found in all other things blind and blockiſh enough) in that he intended and executed, ſhewe himſelfe warie and wiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, furniſhed at the full to anſwere all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, with diſtinctions and exceptions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the preſent matter? and whence came all this but from that viperous broode that had inſtructed and catechized him at the full?</p>
            <p>Was hee not a ſmall while before the villanie performed, preſented vnto Father <hi>Abigny?</hi> to him he diſcouered that he had waighty affayres in hand, and ſhewing him his knife, that had gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon it a Heart, with a croſſe vnderneath to proſper his wicked worke?</p>
            <p>Doe you take for good payment, or for a mocke, that pretended gift of forgetting confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to fruſtrate your authority? Why (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:4147:12"/> to the rule of <hi>Mariana,</hi> by the councell of theſe graue and learned Fathers, or at the leaſt by the aduice of the Viſitor of the Prouince, was this murtherer from his youth, nouriſhed and nurtured among the Ieſuites?</p>
            <p>Neede you (my Lords) any other ground, to giue out your cenſure and ſentence againſt this ſociety, againſt theſe conſpiratours? what elſe is it that you want? Haue not the ſame Actes beene ratified and multiplyed before to our coſts, and griefe, for the perſon of our King?</p>
            <p>Doe not they tell you, that theſe Maxims haue paſſed for Law? hath not the like beene deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and iudged before? are not thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Rules turned into an habite, nay, into nature? Of a truth, the caſe of them that pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the heart of our King by the hands of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaillac,</hi> is all one with theirs that ſtabde the king in the mouth by the hands of <hi>Chaſtell,</hi> whereof they failed aſore by <hi>Barriere.</hi> They haue in time not enboldned onelie, but ſecured the hands and hearts of ſuch as attempt theſe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, but alwayes vnder the ſame Maſters, in the ſame Schooles, and by the ſame Doctrine. There is therefore not a pinne to chooſe in this, whether you will haue the Ieſuites <hi>Rauillacs,</hi> or that <hi>Rauailac</hi> ſhall become a Ieſuite: whether the Ieſuites ſhall be the ſpirit of <hi>Rauailac,</hi> or <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailac</hi> the hand of the Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>Heere (methinkes) I here ſome ſay; If it bee
<pb facs="tcp:4147:12"/> done of ſimplicity, I pardon it and them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but alas theſe poore ſoules, to what purpoſe ſhould they doe this? The king hath alwaies ſhewed them good countenance, he hath much graced them, &amp; more benefited them: Loe, <hi>Peter Cotton</hi> confeſſeth, that he was their protector, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond founder and father.</p>
            <p>Yea, but for all that knowe, that theſe blacke ſowles, the taile of this ſociety, doe them what pleaſure you pleaſe, they will bite at vnawares.</p>
            <p>This poyſon (like the Phiſitions deletories) keep always their venomous condition &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, temper it with what you will, or may. The market that their ſociety aimed at (vnder a Spaniſh founder, attaitour and runagate of <hi>Nauarre)</hi> was indeed the mihgtines and Monarchy of <hi>Spaine. With the leauen, is their whole lumpe of dowe leaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> with this it is ſeaſoned and ſowred, breake and chuſe where you will or pleaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> might bee giuen vnto them peece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale; The king in the meane ſpace hath giuen vnto them his owne heart: they will be ſure to ſaue their owne ſtake, whatſoeuer they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe or come by, they reſerue that alwaies for <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you haue this prooued vnto you? was there euer a greater flatterer, fauourer, I would ſay of our late king, than this good Father himſelf who was late named?</p>
            <p>And yet withall we muſt not forget to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:4147:13"/> vnto you vnder this vizard, his fained reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, his deepe diſſembled humility, his <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens</hi> ſmiles, tended to no other end, but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of the kings reputation, to the hinderance of the good of his affaires, and to what not that might woorke his and our wracke? what let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wrote he, what aduiſe gaue he in <hi>Spaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Ieſuites of <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> what did they with the Captaines that leuied ſupplye to the Regiments for the warres of <hi>Gleueland?</hi> how handled they them when they were confeſſed by them? euen the ſame that Father <hi>Gonteir</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſpeake in his ſermon: That is, that to go againſt the Catholickes, might not be done with a ſafe conſcience, that euery blowe that they ſhould ſtrike vppon any of them, ſtrooke our Lord Chriſt to the heart: becauſe they holde none for Chatholique, but the Catholique king of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is none regiſtred in their Catalogue for a Catholique, but ſuch as haue eaten of that Catholicon, that ſeeketh the ruine of the realme wherein they inhabite.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſtep yet one ſtep higher. Did not thoſe two Ieſuites that followed ſo faſt after my Lord Marſhall of <hi>Chatres,</hi> at ſuch time as he departed to conduct the Armie, inſtruct him in a caſe of conſcience?</p>
            <p>Did they not tell him flatly, that he was dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if hee went forward in his iourney? And
<pb facs="tcp:4147:13"/> if their accuſtomed impudencie would or ſhould deny this, being avouched and averred, by ſo waighty, by ſo graue a witneſſe, were hee not witleſſe that would belieue them? Aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they thought by this deteſtable deuiſe, to haue cut off, and pluckt vp the purpoſe of our late king by the rootes.</p>
            <p>Yet they ſee, that our moſt dread Soueraigne and Queene, purſueth the ſame chace; and is deſirous, that in deſpite of our heauy miſhappe, her woorthye and warre-like Armies ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue.</p>
            <p>Haue recourſe further vnto their accuſtomed practiſes, and you ſhall then diſcerne them in their liuely colours; you ſhall find them voide of all pittie, and piety; Note with what abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſuperſtition they fill the eares &amp; minds of ſuch as liſten vnto them; ſee how they haue cooled or rather vtterly quenched in them, the true worſhip and reuerence of the name of God; how they ſeeke to lead and guide vs by falſe feares, and vaine doubts.</p>
            <p>They would not by their good wills, ſuffer vs to ſtrengthen our frontiers againſt the forage and force of an enemie; the ftontiers of firme friendſhippe; They are vnwilling wee ſhould maintaine and defend the auncient friendes and Allyes of this, or rather according to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Vernin,</hi> the common Allyes of twoo Crownes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:14"/>
            <p>This were (if you will giue them credite) to make you fighr againſt the Goſpell, to wage bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile againſt Heauen; And what can we make of this, but flatte hereſie? And of this hereticall religion, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> (forſooth) could bee content to accuſe and condemne our late king <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, who was a better Catholique then himſelfe; and that euen in his own Realme; wherevpon he ſtudied to remooue his place, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp mutinies againſt him, cauſed his greateſt &amp; moſt principall Cities to reuolte; and all this muſt needs be called Chriſtianitie; this maketh the Actors, true Catholiques; them that dye in ſuch a warre, Martires and their worke, a worke of ſupererogation, not a ſingle merite.</p>
            <p>Will you yet haue an other proofe? Aske of your Ieſuites where their murthering zeale was, then when our late deceaſed king, King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre,</hi> made warre for his Religion, when the Pope excommunicated him, and they like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues openly denounced him for an Hereticke, and one fallen into Relaps?</p>
            <p>It cannot be found in all this time, for the ſpace of fifteene yeares, but that they haue attempted the taking away of his life, becauſe they holde him as a mightie inſtrument to entertaine our Ciuill warres, hoped that he would in ſmall time conſume our forces, and that hee and all our whole Eſtate, ſhould in the end be buried in the aſhes, conſumed and confunded.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:14"/>
            <p>Well, now they ſee hee hath attained the Crowne, that he hath changed his Religion to imbrace that wherof they ſo much vaunt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they call themſelues the Pillers, by that means to enioye the Kingdome quietly, and as they ſuppoſe to become a fearefull eye-ſore to the King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> Now their zeale ſheweth it ſelfe, now their ſpirits are mooued, now they beſtirre their witts and buſie their mindes, now the whole ſwarme of that darke dungeon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their likneſſe, and ſcatter themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in euery corner of our Region and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye.</p>
            <p>In ſuch manner, and after ſuch a ſort, as it is abſolutely ſeene and knowne, that they haue ſharpened, tempered, and whet their malice, fortified and redoubled their accuſtomed and long continued practiſes and deuiſes; and why all this, I pray you?</p>
            <p>Is it for Religions cauſe? Why did they not rather then afore this, when our king was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate? when he was by them denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced hereticke? why is this geere now onely ſet abroach, when he is openly of all men declared, and by their own ſelues acknowledged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to bee a Catholique? And yet for all this they are not aſhamed to warrant vs ſafety againſt theſe vnſaciate murther-moouers, prouided that wee will continue good Catholiques; by this ſlye means ſeeking to change our iuſtly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:4147:15"/> mindes, to turne vs from the execution of that iuſt reuenge, which they haue too iuſtlye called vpon their owne heads.</p>
            <p>They preach vnto vs the banniſhing of the <hi>Hugonets,</hi> againſt them they arme themſelues with tooth and naile. But certainly, if theſe <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonets</hi> were Spaniards, if they would faſhion and frame themſelues to their intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, if they would bee but once regiſtred in their red bloody bookes; I knowe then what they would ſay of them, and how they would deale with them.</p>
            <p>They ſhould ſoone bee purged and purified from this crime &amp; hereſie, and with little a do be made perfect Catholiques, nay, they ſhould haue both themſelues and their Armour ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for ſo ſound a ſeruice. Well be that ſo: in the meane time they importune vs, that there ought to be but one Religion in <hi>France.</hi> They find it conuenient that the Spaniard ſhould make peace with the Eſtates, at the charge of the Maſſe, of our Church, and of the Pope himſelfe; if their diuinity will allowe thereof. For you ſhall neuer heare them ſing other ſong, they themſelues are the onely denouncers of this decree.</p>
            <p>Why haue our Kings (for the quiet of their Eſtate) forbidden preaching, retayning wholye our Religion, and the Pope his authority? And I pray you, why ſhould this action which ought
<pb facs="tcp:4147:15"/> rather be taken in the better part, be accounted Catholiques in the Spaniard, and Hereſie in our Kings? In the end after this ſlander, to pleaſe vs againe; they tell vs wee haue now no more <hi>Hugonets</hi> left then will ſerue for a breakfaſt; thoſe are their owne words; and I would thoſe few might choake them at the firſt morcell.</p>
            <p>What villanies they haue before time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, you haue heard; what miſchiefes they haue not deuiſed onely, but practiſed, you haue ſeene with your eyes; and will you not belieue that this comfort which they pretend, this ſtrange reſtoratiue that they offer, commeth out of the ſame Apothecaries ſhop?</p>
            <p>Are you not perſwaded, that they would, for the accompliſhment of their ioye, that the ſame knife that hath ſlaine our head, ſhould ſmite vs at the heart?</p>
            <p>Of a ſurety, theſe Hugonets (as they tearme them) neuer had any thing of hurt in them that reſembleth theirs: Yet the time was that wee haue burnt them, that we haue proſecuted and perſecuted them in ſo ſtrange manner, as that it hath beene an horror to our owne conſciences: &amp; yet in the middeſt of all their miſeries and our rigours, it was neuer heard or known, that they ſo much as imagined, much leſſe pretended any thing againſt the liues of their Princes, either of King <hi>Charles,</hi> or of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third. Who hath euer accuſed them, ſuſpected them, but he
<pb facs="tcp:4147:16"/> hath ſlaundered them? But on the other ſide, howſoeuer we haue oppreſſed them, iniuried them, impriſoned them, or euer ſo much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them; yet when it came to the vpſhot that there was any vſe to bee made of them, that the enemy aſſaulted or aſſailed the Land, that the ſtranger offered to wrong the Countrie, haue they not been as forward as the beſt of vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend? haue they not drawne their ſwords with ours? nay, haue they not receaued woundes with vs, and loſt their bloud with ours? By this meanes (as euery one knoweth) our Eſtate ſtood in ſafety.</p>
            <p>Theſe kind of people that are moſt readie, then to kill Princes when they moſt commend them; that haue vowed to weare no weapon, but for the death of a King; that teach, that murther is the high and ready way to heauen, if any enquire it at their hands; dare they now adaies ſpeake of baniſhing? eſpeciallie our Countrimen, our Neighbours, our Friends, our Fathers our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, our kindred, nay, our owne fleſh and bloud, that are ſo readie to runne to relieue vs in our dangers.</p>
            <p>Doe they holde vs for ſo blunt and blockiſh, as that wee cannot ſee into their ſubtiltie, who haue already (ſo without all pittie and mercie) opened the Baſilike and Cephalicke vaines (that I may vſe the tearmes of that good Father <hi>Guig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard)</hi> vnder pretence to let vs bloud for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe
<pb facs="tcp:4147:16"/> of Hereſie; that they goe about to cut in peeces both the ſinewes and Arteries, yea of the Catholiques themſelues? for, is it poſsible (if this courſe were taken) but that bloud ſhould be ſhed on both ſides, and both parties periſh? And all this notwithſtanding, to the heart-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of all good Frenchmen, they muſt haue our hearts and good wills at their commaund, To them bee the impudency, and to vs the ſhame. Let them come to aske vs Rent, after the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts are caſt vp, and the reckoning full made. How full of miſteries they are in all their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and doings.</p>
            <p>And this among the reſt is none of the leaſt miſteries, for they thinke they haue wonne the game, they take it that they haue gotten the goale, that they haue what they would haue. Who doubteth but that they will take this for a Trophie, a Trophie or Tryumph of their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of their magnanimity, but a badge and cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of our ſimplicity, or to ſpeake more plaine, ſottiſhnes?</p>
            <p>What cauſe then haue we to comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them? what reaſon to reward or regard them? Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue ſlaine him, is it becauſe they haue murthered him? for what <hi>Chastell</hi> hath done, they did.</p>
            <p>Is it their funerall Orations that you ſo honor? in the prime and pride of all their Rethoricke, of all their eloquence, their was hardly one La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb facs="tcp:4147:17"/> ſentence, or French phraze, that tended to his good that was dead, and for that I pray you pardon them.</p>
            <p>There was neuer thing heard ſo colde, ſo weake, ſo witleſſe. They were ſo choaked with the ioye of his death, ſo ouer ioyed with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his murther, as that they had quite &amp; cleane forgotten the ſorow due to our common griefe, and the praiſes due to his worthy life.</p>
            <p>Wretched thing that it is, to haue procured to them ſuch honour, nay, ſuch pleaſure; and vnto <hi>France</hi> ſuch a perpetual reproach, ſo immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſhame: ſhall I euer forget that thou haſt a hand in this vnhappineſſe? When they choſe thee in their affaires and buſineſſes, as Protector, and Procurer, diddeſt thou not perceaue theſe Hippocrites, the ſhadowes of ſanctimonie, how they curteſied and courted thee, how they ſought and ſolicited thee, at thine vpriſing, at thy downe-lying, to the end, that by thy credite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the decree of a moſt ſoueraigne Court, a decree pronounced by the bleeding mouth of thy diſtreſſed Maſter, they might be recalled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France</hi> againe.</p>
            <p>Thinkeſt thou, that if the Court had giuen thee neuer ſo little incouragement, it had been fot good, or for euill? for their praiſe, or for their diſpraiſe? had it been conuenient that they ſhould ſo ſtrumpet-like, vildely, and villanouſly proſtitute their ſhamefaſtnes to thy ſhame?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:17"/>
            <p>They, whoſe pride is well knowne to haue no other purpoſe, but to broke and buye our ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, thongh it be valued at the rate of their high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhame, are they not worthy to bee ſhunned? And among the reſt, thou thy ſelfe (ſith thou art not borne to die for griefe) were it not fit that thou ſhouldeſt come to the Court with an halter about thy necke, creeping on thy belly, clad in ſacke-cloth and aſhes, to craue of him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Iuſtice? pardon for thy brutiſhneſſe, that art ſo neare in fault to a fault ſo monſtrous, in that thou haſt preſumed vppon a fauour moſt vnworthily giuen thee, in cauſes belonging to kings, to doe againſt the lawes; ignorant and infamous perſon that thou art: Iuſtice againſt thoſe haue blindfolded thee, bewitched thee, made thee the inſtrument of thy Mayſters mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of ſuch a Maiſter, as from the dunghill hath raiſed and enritched thee (without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart of thine) as againſt all reaſon; ſo beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and nature. But (my Lords) it may be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cottons</hi> declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ſatisfied you, blot out his ſuſpitions. Put him ouer to be examined by our Abbot, by our Clergie men, that can better handle this matter than you: &amp; yet it were good to haue an eye to the maine, in as much as the caſe ſtood otherwiſe, before my L. Chancellor, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his grauity and wiſedome corrected it. They are reproached with that famous booke of D. <hi>Iohn Mariana,</hi> which breatheth out nothing
<pb facs="tcp:4147:18"/> elſe, but poiſon and ſlaughter. They make vs belieue it is a very badde booke.</p>
            <p>In our Ieſuites Calapine, might not a man (thinke you) picke out ſome one word or other, that may bring this booke into deteſtation? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne mouth ſpeaketh ſo maydenly of his owne worke, what doth he leaue vs to coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his heart? Thus himſelfe ſpeaketh of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>This booke of mine (ſaith he) is but the ſlight paſſage of an euill cut pen; Is he to be acquitted, to be cleared, for theſe gallant Metaphors, for theſe glozing far-fetcht, borrowed phraſes? whereas this execrable doctrine of his that hath paſſed currant without contradiction theſe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteene yeres, ſauoureth of nothing elſe but miſchiefe and murther, and that not againſt meane men, but the mightieſt, it aymeth at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but Kings and Princes?</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, what charity, what iuſtice were this, that for one <hi>Mariana,</hi> the whole ſociety ſhould ſuffer? And why not? for it is the whole ſociety that ſpeaketh and offendeth in <hi>Mariana:</hi> for it appeareth by his owne mouth, by his own aſſertions and atteſtations, that the graueſt and moſt learned of that ſect and ſort haue taken a view thereof, the Prouinciall and Viſitor haue allowed of it, the Generall taken order that it ſhould be imprinted, to haue it acknowledged for a moſt Autenticke woorke of that ſociety:
<pb facs="tcp:4147:18"/> what greater ceremonie would they haue then this? what other forme of confirmation? But let vs farther ſaye, it is not one <hi>Mariana</hi> alone, that hath written of this matter, of this ſubiect; The Ieſuites of all Nations, of all Climates, haue prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized this Apoſtleſhippe, haue publiſhed this Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emanuell Sa:</hi> the Portugall; <hi>Gabriell Vaſques,</hi> and <hi>Peter Ribadineira</hi> Spaniards; <hi>Martin Beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bonarſius,</hi> baſe Almains; <hi>Iohn Guignard,</hi> and the Authors of the Apologie of <hi>Chaſtell,</hi> Frenchman; <hi>Robert Bellarmine</hi> Italian; <hi>Ioſeph Creſwell</hi> Engliſhman: and many others haue executed the ſelfe ſame practiſe with ioynt conſent, vpon the perſons of Kings and Princes, in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> in the lowe Countries, and of late memotie in <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> where there was but one onely; ſo contagious and corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue is this poiſon wherſoeuer it catcheth hold, whereſoeuer it ſeazeth.</p>
            <p>Our dolefull miſchiefe was knowne at <hi>Prage,</hi> at <hi>Madrill,</hi> at <hi>Brucells,</hi> before it came vnto vs, as the Ambaſſors euer truely iuſtified: and all this done, by the moſt accurſed correſpondence of that company.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let vs all iumpe in this which is a thing more then certaine, that whether it bee their beſt Diuines, their moſt authorized Doctors, Prouincialls, Generalls, Cardinalls, pretended Martires, or whoſoeuer elſe of that raſcally rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:4147:19"/> they haue all conſpired and knotted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together, to no better intent than is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy alleadged. For as touching any thing that they can ſaye for themſelues, to cleare their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed cauſe, it is ſo weake, ſo withered, ſo darke, ſo double; ſo ſpoken in the teeth, ſo tumbled out; that there is no one ſo ſimple or ſo ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, but that he may with eaſe iudge, that it is the doctrine of Equiuocants, the doctrine of D. <hi>Navarre</hi> that is ſpoken.</p>
            <p>But we (ſaye they) in our congregation Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall held at <hi>Paris,</hi> requeſted of the Generall of our company, that whoſoeuer had written to the preiudice of the crowne of <hi>France,</hi> he ſhould be puniſhed, and his booke ſuppreſſed.</p>
            <p>Now note (my good Lords) what hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened fifteene yeres after, when this poyſon had leiſure to runne throughout all the vaines, and let them preduce but any one if they can, what hath beene excommunicate or otherwiſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, for this booke, or for any the like?</p>
            <p>Or let vs our ſelues remember what Curate wee haue knowne ſolemnly in the Church, to haue but threatned Hell to ſuch a Diuell as theſe Ieſuites are? yea, ſaye you, but there was one cenſured, true: but why I pray you? forſooth, for telling tales out of the ſchoole; for too open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and too ſeuerely publiſhing their ſecrets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. And to what end I pray you was this great peece of ſeruice done? ſurely to as great purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:4147:19"/> as that that <hi>Rauailac</hi> did: to let fall the knife af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had ſtrooke the fatall blowe, burne the booke after they had fired their hearts, by the meanes of all theſe hell hound ſpirits of <hi>Europe.</hi> But made he not as good a confeſsion of his faith to the Queene?</p>
            <p>It is to bee ſeene (ſaith he) in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> &amp;c. What better thing could he haue ſpoken? Here beginneth their inchaunting ſongs. For before they can drawe to an end, all kind of deceit, both in woord and worke, is permitted vnto them; fraude is the beſt part of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and of their Rules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not good to buye and ſell, not conuenient to traffique at all, with Marchants of this mould and mettall:</hi> And yet are wee ſo mightily blinde, that we make no conſcience voluntarily to thruſt our ſelues into their hands, to bee bought and ſolde by them. Let vs a while heare this Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <note place="margin">Cardinall <hi>Toledo</hi> in his Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotall inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, bo. 4, chap. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Toledo:</hi> the firſt man that <hi>Peter Cotten</hi> doth produce vnto vs, in his Sacerdotall Inſtitution. Marke how hee inſtructeth his Prieſts: beeing (ſaith he) after an oath taken, demanded his ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to anſwere to any queſtions, he may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe equiuocation, and is not bound to anſwere according to the will of the Iudge, but after his own mind and diſcretion: yea, if it bee in an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence knowne vnto him, or elſe committed by him; he may thus ſhift it off; I know not, or I did it not; meaning; what I may ſay or do hereafter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:20"/>
            <p>In like manner <hi>Siluanus:</hi> It is lawfull to vſe equiuocations and doubtfull woordes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue <note place="margin">Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uanus in his Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipik. p. 5.</note> the hearers; when he that demandeth the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not your own Superior or Iudge. And of late, they haue ſet it down for a ſure ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorke and foundation; that no Clarke is or neede be ſubiect to any ſecular perſon, no not to his owne naturall Prince.</p>
            <p>What confidence, what truth or truſt, may a man then repoſe vpon their oathes? vpon the depoſition of this good Father ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Valence</hi> vſeth the like ſpeaches, <note place="margin">Tome 3. diſputa. 5. queſt. 13.</note> commended by that faction for a man of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent learning; well knowne in <hi>Spame, Italie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Germanie:</hi> he, writing vpon a booke called the Sonne, nameth this ſcience of Equiuocation; A prudent defence, practized by <hi>Garnet</hi> Prouincial in <hi>England,</hi> with a braſen face, and a moſt irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious heart; and reduced into an Art by Doctor <hi>Martin Navarre</hi> Ciuilian, in a booke compoſed for that purpoſe: in fauour (for thoſe bee his woordes) of the moſt excellent ſocietie of the Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>But will you heare the bewitching ſongs of theſe lewde Syrens, before wee part from this Narration? Our Kings (ſaith he) in <hi>Fraunce</hi> be the eldeſt Children of the Church: would you not thinke he had flattered the Queene well, and giuen her good words? And yet the Equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:4147:20"/> that bewrayeth the villanie is apparant, in that that he ſayth; our Kings in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and not of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> If he ſhould haue ſaid of <hi>France;</hi> he feared the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> leaſt he ſhould take exceptions at him for his compariſon, wherein he ſeemeth to preferre the King of <hi>France</hi> before all the kings of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>But in that he ſaith in <hi>France,</hi> he excludeth the compariſon, and doth reſtraine their preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue within the bounds and Lymits of their own Realme. And by this drift in the middle of his owne natiue <hi>Fraunce,</hi> hee lodgeth the heart of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus woont to ſpeake to our late dread king, in recommendation of their founder <hi>Loyola:</hi> that hee was his ſubiect, which cauſed the King to thinke he had beene a French man: And being taken with the manner in his equiuocation, hee put it off thus, that hee was of <hi>Navarre,</hi> as being neuer without a hole to creepe out at.</p>
            <p>But he was warie enough for telling him that he was Traitor, both to the King and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that he defended <hi>Pampelune,</hi> againſt the king his Grandfather, where hee was hurt, and in a madneſſe made himſelfe a Monke: and now at laſt a Father among vs, and very well woorthy, for he is the father of many periuries and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>The queſtion is asked, what ſhall we then do? And doe you doubt, all this conſidered, what is
<pb facs="tcp:4147:21"/> to be done?</p>
            <p>Truely (my Lords) if my councell might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, you ſhould vſe them like Scorpions, kill them, and laye them to their ſting and our wounds; but let vs deale a little more mildely. What leſſe can bee done, then to execute your decree with ſpeed and ſeueritie? doe you thinke that to condemne them, is to condemne you? that to ſhew them iuſtice, is to challenge you of iniuſtice?</p>
            <p>Or would you haue it ſayd (which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend) that theſe Monſters increaſe both in offence and impudency; and you that are Guardians of this Eſtate; as though you had loſt your wits, ſhould faile in vertue, and faint in iuſtice?</p>
            <p>All Chriſtian Eſtates haue taken their patterne from you, euen to the bounds and borders of all Europe, the Almaines, Hungarians, Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, haue baniſhed them their Lands and Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, as ignoble, vnwoorthy to liue vnder any honeſt Laws, vnder any Ciuill gouernment; &amp; by expreſſe decree in theſe prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeignories, they haue determined not to recall them, whatſoeuer reaſons <hi>Rome</hi> can alledge, whatſoeuer inſtance it bringeth. And yet <hi>Rome</hi> is very neere <hi>Italy,</hi> and therefore the ſooner likely to bee afraid? And this they haue doone by a diuine prouidence, by a liuely apprehenſion of what may happen. Is there any miſchiefe of greater moment, than what they haue already committed? Can there
<pb facs="tcp:4147:21"/> bee any thing more monſtrous, then what they haue already practiſed? Is it poſſible to giue a more vilde name to a villanous practize, then a generall murther, an vniverſall ſlaughter? And would it not on the other ſide bee thought very ſtrange, that you ſhould beare ſo vneauen a ballance, weigh things with ſuch inequality, that your example ſhould make Lawes vnto other, and not be obſerued of your ſelues? Your lawes ſtand in ſtead of wholeſome precautions, and preuentions to your neighbours, to thoſe that dwell a farre off, to thoſe that are not ſo ſicke, not ſo diſeaſed as you are; and will you make no vſe of them in ſo preſent and preſsing a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe?</p>
            <p>Belieue it, and looke for no other, that if wee doe dallie and delay to cure or cut off this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerons ſore that now breedeth among vs; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more grieuous paines will followe a freſh.</p>
            <p>Would one ſore thinke you bee incarnate, would it be cloſed, ſeemeth it readye to cicca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trize? It is a ſtrange caſe in euery Country, and in euery body, ſauing in <hi>Spaine;</hi> they haue pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified our humor, they haue corrupted our bloud, whereof ſpringeth Apoſthumation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamation, feuers, rupture of the fleſh; which the longer it doth laſt, the harder it will be to heale: but on the other ſide, purge it once well, cleare the vlcer; fleſh and bloud that wee are one of
<pb facs="tcp:4147:22"/> another, the lippes will growe together againe, and the hurt will heale alone.</p>
            <p>Yea marrie, you ſaye well, but to banniſh ſo great a ſociety, for the offence of one onelie, were not ſtrange? You ſaye ſomewhat; yet I muſt tell you, the concluſion of your argument hardly agreeth with his promiſes. It is this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety that ſtrooke that luckleſſe ſtroake, not hee that held the knife: it was their Councell, their doctrine, their coniuration: It is already known and convinced, in the arrainment and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Chaſtell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did the Iewes euer commit the like, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a whole race? Or the Templers, in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to baniſh all others to eſtabliſh their order? But ſaith another, what ſhall become of good Letters? how ſhall Learning doe, which theſe worthie men teach ſo worſhipfully? how ſhall our youth doe? If thou be an Aſſe or an Idyot, I pardon thee that askeſt the queſtion.</p>
            <p>When they came firſt into our <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> were our Vniuerſities a ſleepe? So many great perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſo learned, ſo graue, as haue beene there brought vp fiftie yeares agoe, which haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured all <hi>Europe:</hi> not their owne Country onely; were they of their inſtruction? followed they their methode? As for their Schooles what hath euer come out of them, worthy the talking of? Of a truth, if as the Scottiſhmen did long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, vnder <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; they ſhould come
<pb facs="tcp:4147:22"/> and call and crie about the ſtreetes, who would buy learning without any further meaning, without thruſting their ſickles into other mens harveſts, or without medling with other mens matters, they had been to be borne withall, nay they ſhould haue byn welcome, euen to the beſt learned. But are we now to learne, that vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this good Latin, they fill our children with very evill French? that vnder the ſhew of good letters, and wholeſome ſciences, they confound our Spirites, and corrupt our ſoules? See wee not how in the end, they inſenſibly tranſforme our affections and our wils in this tender age: to faſhion, vs and in vs by this meanes in their Colledges, ſo many Spaniſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies, ſpredde abroad and founded within the bulke of all our bloud, as therby they alter (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their vilde and baſe qualities which they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print there) all the body of the Realme. So, as to buy Latine and learning at this rate, it were better we neuer knew what latine ment, or euer ſpake other then our own language. Yea but be not ſo ſuperſtitious; what man, baniſh this good and godly name of <hi>Ieſus;</hi> can you thus without ſhame and ſinne, kicke againſt the holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine? what a number of good deuotions, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſsions ſhall we looſe with them? Nay ſay rather, how many diuels how many deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes? Antiquity called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuotes, that vowed their liues for the death of any one, at any doleful actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:23"/>
            <p>What other deuotion is there among theſe, ſo woorthy the noting, as this? But not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture their owne liues, they are too carefull and cunning in that: but to perſwade and bring others vnto it.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, whether call you it loſſe or gaines to looſe ſuch deuotes? For, as for any other ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all marke of holyneſſe, if you looke for in them; they will ſend you to the <hi>Indians;</hi> there are their Martires, there are their miracles. This wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched weſt-part of the world, is neither capable nor worthy of them.</p>
            <p>Among vs they can produce no other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres but Chaſtells, Rauailaks, Fathers, Garnets, Guignards, Guerets, murtherers of Kings: bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Realmes: for their miracles, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto you; ſeditions, conſpiracies, murthers, maſſacres.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that among vs feede and fill themſelues with nothing elſe, but ſlaine bodies, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered carkafles, ſhall we bee ſo fooliſh as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that in other places they raiſe the dead, yea, or ſo much as heale the diſeaſed? And as touching confeſsion, the chiefe ſinew of their ſocietie, or rather of their coniuration; who knoweth not, that it is nothing elſe but a Caball of that old Mahumetan of the Mountaine, vſed to confirme and reſolue thoſe that are his, to kill chriſtian Princes in the holy Land. They tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport their Nouices (caſting them into a ſleepe
<pb facs="tcp:4147:23"/> with certaine drinkes) into a certaine place, where they not onely ſee, but taſte all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of their holy Fathers prophane Paradice: to the end (that waking) they may deſpiſe the danger and death that they might runne into by killing of Kings; a death whereof when they haue taſted, ſhould bring vnto them ioye euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p>In their confeſsions ſuch is their craft, (for Sathan alwaies profiteth by growing olde) they draw from all the horrible offences that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they haue committed; And that reuealed, they plunge them ouer the head and ſhoulders in the horror of that eternall paine, that is allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſo heauie ſinnes, and after in their cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, giue them a feeling of heauenly Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Afterwardes, when they haue thus broken the heads and hearts of them, when they haue thus aſtoniſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they propound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſome one offence, an ordinary murde; of ſome other ſin, the killing of a King at the leaſt; and ſo of the reſt: which if they will attempt and accompliſh, they will warrant, that it ſhall not onely free him of iuſtly deſerued paine; but beſides, according to the nature of that that hee ſhall practiſe, as vpon a noble man, a Prince, a King; his rewarde ſhall proportioned more, or leſſe in Heauen; As to bee an Angell, or Archangell, &amp;c. And thus they furniſh with
<pb facs="tcp:4147:24"/> a conſecrated weapon: ſaying, take the ſword of <hi>Dauid,</hi> of <hi>Iudith,</hi> of <hi>S. Peter:</hi> Aſſone as they haue deliuered it vnto him, ſtraight they honor him, they admire him, they worſhip him. They perſwade him that hee is already deified, they find him transfigured, glorified.</p>
            <p>Doe you not thinke that they haue well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched the Sarazines invention? This Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane vſed this practiſe of his, but onely againſt his enemies, as he tooke them, infidels; but our mercy more carefull a great deale then this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, make vſe thereof onely againſt Chriſtians; they reſerue it by a ſpeciall priuiledge for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted Kings, thoſe eſpecially whom Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome calleth moſt Chriſtian among the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. In briefe, the pretended wiſedome tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs (I pray God it be not wickedneſſe) that to deale with ſo great a bodie, ſo mighty a ſociety, cannot be without much danger: And who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth his Holyneſſe will make vs feare and feele his power? and yet we muſt needs be affraid of ſome hundred or not many more, that are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad, heere, and there, in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? Such as haue no part or portion in our Eſtate, that haue nothing to doe with any of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, Cities, or Families, ſuch as we can eaſily roote out, without beeing ſeene or perceiued Shall theſe hinder you for doing iuſtice, iuſtice vnto our King, iuſtice for ſo haynous an acte? where (my good Lords) ſhould your auncient
<pb facs="tcp:4147:24"/> vertue become? whome ſhould it meete with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in his way, in the way of iuſtice to hinder you? <hi>Cerberus</hi> with his three heads, ſhould bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to creepe on his belly (as our King was wont to ſay) hee would leaue to doe the iuſtice of God, for the pleaſure of men: of that God which is alwaies able, to ſtrengthen the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man in his affaires. Aſſuredly, my Lords, he promiſeth the ſame ayde to you at this daye. Nay, the preſent necesſity, extreamitie, and iuſt dolour, will confirme and redouble ſtrength in you. But to giue the ancient ſtrength and vigor to his Eſtate, requireth your helping hand; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you firſt ſtrong and couragious, and they will ſoone follow. Let vs know by the ſpeedy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of your decree, what feeling, what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiou there is in you, let nothing hinder, let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtaye that? And doe you not repoſe your ſelues (my Lords) vppon the quaint deuiſes of theſe companions, vppon their ſuppoſes, vppon their ſupports; this voice of mine is the voice of all <hi>France,</hi> nay of all the Catholicks of this realme. Our fields, our Townes, our Artes, doe rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand at your hands our King, that cauſed them to floriſh, to flowre to preuaile, to profit. They all ſigh and ſob for this iuſtice. Our Clergie cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from you their defender, the Nobles their guide our people their deliuerer, our eſtate their reſtorer, the ſoundeſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, our French Princes the honour of their bloud, Strangers the Captaine of their Ranckes. </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:25"/>
            <p>There is nothing that can gaineſay, or gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriue this requeſt. Theſe trickling teares, theſe ſecret murmurings, this aſtoniſhed ſilence hath no other wiſh, nor ſpeaketh any other ſpeech. To be ſhort, the earth that hath giuen entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his ſacred bloud ſpilt vpon a pauement (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) that will neuer be dry; cryeth vengeance of the Heauens; <hi>The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens receaue their voices, and rebound from thence a commaund of the ſame reuenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot better (my Lords) continue and increaſe the yeares of our King, comfort the teares of the Queene, nor better bewaile the death of <hi>Henrie</hi> the Great, moane his ſorrowfull death, celebrate his obſequies, nor conſecrate his memory to eternity. By this meanes you ſhall beſt continue and defend your Nobilities and places, you ſhall bee Fathers of your Country, if you will truely the voice of your Country, and otherwiſe not, which long may you doe and happily.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4147:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
